get
ready showing that Anonymous
Communications already is bloodly
difficult to do at scale uh and
sensorship resistant that was not
achieved uh but thankfully fixed and
improved uh after numerous uh software
updates uh all tour relays are are much
more stable now and hidden services are
are much more stable and in the short
near-term future we will have a complete
a complete rewriting of of the tour
protocol in Rust uh called uh RT another
rust tour implementation uh and it will
be quite Monumental step step shift
Improvement for Tor uh it will be much
more modular and and people will will be
able to configure it and run on numerous
different devices much more powerfully
uh so this is a big Locker for us to to
make privacy Anonymous transactions work
at scale having a reliable anonymity
network but thankfully TOS improving
rapidly uh there's also know a couple
other alternative approaches uh to onion
routing like for example i2p or the need
mix nuts with Nim and cut post both of
them are really picking up steam and and
and shipping actual code um and and in
Bitcoin we can make improvements to the
network layer privacy as well uh bid 324
it is called I think opportunistic uh
Network encryption for Bitcoin where
finally we have encryption in the
Bitcoin protocol in the sense that when
you talk to another peer on the Bitcoin
Network to get a block or to broadcast a
transaction finally that will be
encrypted uh and no longer clear text on
the buyer so that any internet service
provider can snip up the traffic uh and
the beautiful thing is that this
encryption scheme results in a perfectly
random bitstream of data uh that the
cipher text uh so that any any outside
protocol who would like to look
indistinguishable and like Bitcoin just
needs to produce indistinguishably
random bites and it could be Bitcoin
traffic or it could be that other
application that is using the same PE
to-peer encryption standard as Bitcoin
right we we've we've created a nice pool
of anonymity that starts out with
Bitcoin users but can be a bunch of
other users in the future um also useful
still with if you use the door network
not as much um and and then on bitcoin
uh well I I think onchain privacy is
solved at this point Wasabi 2.0 as it
stands now it's a a good enough um
solution to making blockchain
transactions that are fully Anonymous
the trick is super simple just make
really large transactions because inside
the Bitcoin transactions we already have
perfectly Anonymous value transfer there
is no cryptographic link between the
second input paid the fifth output that
doesn't exist all outputs get destroyed
and atomically all outputs get uh get
created sorry inputs destroyed outputs
created uh and there is no flow of
thingss in between perfectly Anonymous
as good as ecash in fact um the only
downside is in the past we built really
small Bitcoin transactions where we have
really small anonymity sets inside a
transaction but if we increase the size
of the crow add more inputs and outputs
to the transaction we can benefit from
bitcoin's native anonymity uh that
provides that is super strong actually
um and we can now leverage these uh
these large onchain transactions to do
all types of other things like for
example opening lightning network
channels uh the lightning network is is
a way to uh send Bitcoin but without
requiring a global consensus update
right not everyone has to read and
validate this this transaction uh only
the peers in the channel and the people
along the route of multiple payment
channels need to keep up of this payment
uh in in order to to settle it um that's
a great privacy Improvement that's a
great scalability Improvement and it's
not bullet or battle tested for the last
four or five years um and and working
quite well by now um but we can improve
the privacy of lightning even more uh by
for example using coin joints to open
and close lightning network channels one
of the big problems right now when you
uh do onchain transaction with your
lightning note just by looking at the
blockchain I can still see
a lot of activity that's happening I
might find out that these five payment
channels in fact belong to the same
person because they were all created in
a appealing chain for example um or they
were closed together in the same DCH
transaction um there are uh so coin
joints improve or fix blockchain level
privacy and we can use lightning
networks blockchain anchoring uh to just
upgrade it with conj and make sure that
nobody knows that this input paid that
output and that in fact is a a payment
Channel and or that these multiple
payment channels belong to the same note
just by looking at offchain activity and
leveraging the solutions of layer one to
make sure that layer two is is even more
secure um another thing that we added in
layer one was was T rot schor signatures
which is a a mindblowing Improvement um
because signatures are fundamentally
very simple very elegant signature
scheme that can be built to abstract a
lot of other really really cool stuff um
the classical of course is multi
signature or or music um whereas in the
early days of big Qui the verifier
needed to know that there are three
public keys that should authorize this
transaction and two of those them are
required so the verifier needed to know
the individual public keys that are in
the multi signature and how many public
keys there are what's the threshold
right and which public Keys signed all
of this was was revealed to the verifier
versus now with with schnor we have
music meaning we can and aggregate those
keys where 100 public keys are
aggregated to a single public key and 70
or or 80 or whatever out of these get uh
have to sign in order to produce a
single valid signature valid for this
public key um we can do this for multi
signature schemes so 100 out of 100 or
we can do this for threshold schemes
like two out of three um uh and with the
threshold scheme there's even another
crazy cool thing that if you have a two
out of three Frost or a rose signature
scheme then the two people can kick out
the third one right uh uh and make an
offchain key rotation U where some some
magic but I don't quite understand uh
the the third person can no longer be
part of creating a valid signature um
and you can add new participants into
this multi signature uh and even I think
increase the threshold scheme as well so
changing a two out of three multi
signature to a to a four out of five for
example uh and all of that without CH
without making a blockchain transaction
and without changing the public key
that's referenced on the Bitcoin
blockchain right um and so this means
that lightning channels which are two
out of two multi signatures look
indistinguishable from a one one out of
one single signature schema or from 11
out of 15 um liquid Federation as right
um and we have TS inputs and outputs
already right now in B Co right for
multiple months there could be multi
users in in these Co transactions
or not um or you could be a lightning
that channel open closing um and that uh
that provides a lot of ambiguity uh that
that improves the the first layer of
privacy and also the second layer of
privacy uh another big part in lightning
is routing payments it's not just about
the payment channels it's about making a
payment to someone else whom you don't
have a direct payment channel to uh and
in this case we use currently hash time
contracts which is basically a a message
and you hash it uh so we have a
pre-image and and a hash and you say uh
you commit to the payment by here is a
hash and you get uh like I pay you if
you reveal me the secret basically um uh
and we can do this also with signatures
another cool trick of of the shore
signature schemes adapter signatures um
and point time locked contracts another
crazy signature scheme that some weird
bitcoiners figured out because we want
to optimize the out of signatures
we can like add encrypted signatures
basically that that reveal information
that other people need in order to spend
um a their to in order to create El and
signature uh so we can now route a
payment through the lightning Network
where not a single hop in the route
knows that he's on the same route right
uh they it could be any route that goes
through each time ROM but in fact it's
it's a single chain um a great
Improvement to the lightning routing uh
Pro problem um which is yet another on
routing system similar to toor um uh
another cool thing we can do is blinded
routes uh part of the bolt 12 invoice
scheme and lightning so when you request
someone to get paid you can tell them
not hey this is my public key of the
lightning note that I want to get paid
in but you say look over there there's
there is a public key you can route to
this lightning note and give him this
piece of cycle text and that route can
figure out the next top who incs a piece
of Life effects to figure out the next
top to figure out the next top to
finally end up with me meaning that
finally this the the receiver no longer
has to reveal his public key and his
node identity in order to get paid uh
basically hidden services in in in the
tour L Shan in the sense of they can be
either um they can either you can either
reveal it directly hey this is the the
public key please reach me here or you
can run an anonymous hidden service
which adds multiple hops um blinded in
for each requ so that even the the the
receiver of the message in tour Network
can stay private the same aspect works
in the lightning network with P paths um
so lightning network is is is is cool
and all and and it helps scale us but
it's it's not ultimately the the b and
end all there is classic old Tech um
ecash uh that is a a privacy miracle and
a scalability miracle uh it's super fast
it's free a tiny piece of data has to be
transferred in a single round and that's
it uh and it it can right now today
satisfy billions of users um just from a
technological scalability point of view
uh and here the the only downside is it
is a a money Warehouse receipt in the
sense of you have Bitcoin under your own
full control self custodial and you can
hand over the big man to someone else
who gives you a paper certificate saying
yeah Whoever has this piece of paper can
get the SATs back or the gold back uh
the same idea just instead of a physical
piece of paper digital signature uh
which can be fully blinded um meaning
that every time uh someone deposits at
Tois to to my My Vault my my money
Warehouse I hand out the signature and
when later the same person comes back
with that signature now unblinded um he
I can redeem the satoshis knowing that
someone has deposited them but I have no
idea who it was uh and and this allows
us to have really fast fully private
transactions of of anything basically
including Deb certificates or money
Warehouse certificates so cashu is a
really promising project that enables
this right now very fast very scalable
um issuance of anonymous tokens that can
be redeemed and and the ker here is that
you can be the mint it is a super simple
piece of code that you can run on your
laptop uh to offer these ecash Services
um with the problem of there's a single
issue super simple super fast uh but
that one person can run book you uh it
does not only work for the money
substitute uh aspect but also for for
example Anonymous access rights to an
API this is how Wasabi bed uses ecash
since 2018 um not as you give me SATs
and you get a piece of paper and you can
redeem that paper for SATs later but
instead you call the first API call in
put registration and you get an e-cash
credential and with this e-cash
credential you can do the second API
call output registration and I only
allow the second API call output
registration if there is a valid e cach
right so uh this this token that's super
fast and easy to transact with can also
be used to for example have Anonymous
access rights to a bpn uh or to API like
the coin join or a payall or or truly
anything
um another set of improvement probably
invented here in prag on on both a
conceptual level with script and on the
implementation level with with fent is
Federated ecat where we no longer have a
single computer that has the magic
private key to issue these um these
tokens but it's that a Federation of
three out of five or uh or something
else uh where uh if one of these mints
is malicious still you you are secure
right because there are other
participants in in the bank or in the a
provider that that check the other
participants right so a rogue actor
cannot run away with your money um but a
majority of the service providers still
can right so it's it's a clear
Improvement but it comes with a lot of
extra complexity as soon as you try
stuff in a Federated or decentralized
way it it blows up into complexity um
and and that's where there are big
benefits over centralized systems like
kashu and and wasabi um or
wabisabi versus the Federated model of
fman um we both are very useful but very
often the trade also of the centralized
model makes sense too um uh and well
there's there's even more com right
because there there are uh RGB is
another extremely interesting um project
that really adds a lot of privacy to to
Everyday transactions uh the idea is
again not to have a global consensus um
about this current state of of who has
how many tokens um but instead to have a
only the client valid
how many tokens exist and who has them
etc for uh and uh well this is is a very
private and a very scalable aspect
because not everyone needs to know every
transaction of everyone else very
similar with the lightning Network um
but with RGB this this is more of a
general computation platform so um a bit
similar to fediman where where we can
run quite complex smart contracts uh in
this Federated environment uh similar is
possible with RGB uh where where smart
contracts can for example Express uh
tokens uh both fible and and
non-fungible or or digital identities
Etc um uh and these can be transacted uh
in in a way that it is double spending
protected meaning you can only send it
once and and not a million times to many
people uh but in in a very efficient and
very private manner um so I I I think in
in just this this short overview we can
really see that that private is is at
the Forefront of mine for for a lot of
different Bitcoin projects and the
effort of the last couple years is is
really sh um the the code is is being
shipped for basically everything that
I'm saying now um and can be used right
now uh or at least in the very near-term
future so it's a pretty bright uh view
ahead I think these 10 years of the
hackers Congress have really shown what
a bunch of people can build in a rather
short time uh and and if we look back to
the technology sta that we have had in
in 2023 uh 2013 um it's nothing of what
I said existed but but it is here now
and and we can use it now and just
imagine that same progress extrapolated
for the next 10 years and probably even
more so uh so it will be it will be a
breathtaking future where we can see of
what the next generation of of cyun is
going to build with all of these new
building blocks that that we have now
discovered and and defined um because
the the next levels on top are going to
be Qui um so the near-term future of
anonymous transaction is looking pretty
damn good I think we got to cover it
thank you very
much